YIVO Archives. Interviews in Amerikaner Yiddishe Geschichte Bel-Pe. 6036/002
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
YIVO Archives. Interviews in Amerikaner Yiddishe Geschichte Bel-Pe.
1963- 1964
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
YIVO Institute for Jewish Research
Howe, Irving
6036/002
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
Transcripts of oral history interviews conducted at the Yivo Institute for Jewish Research between 1963 and 1965.
5767221
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, August 26, 2011
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, January 10, 2013
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains transcripts of oral history interviews with veterans of the Jewish labor movement conducted at the YIVO Institute for Jewish Research between 1963 and 1965. They were conducted in conjunction with Professor Irving Howe of the City University of New York. Howe was accumulating material and research in preparation of writing a large volume on immigrant Jews in the U.S., Yiddish culture, and the Jewish labor movement. Many of the transcripts are in Yiddish.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 6036/003: YIVO Project. Interviews in the Irving Howe Collection conducted by Bernard Rosenberg.
Jewish labor unions.; Belson, Abe.; Gershin, Julius.; Goldman, Abraham.; Gutterman, Joseph.; Held, Adolph.; Lipsky, Louis.; Nelson, Louis.; Newman, Pauline.; Rabinovitch, Benjamin.; Rogoff, Hyman.; Wisotsky, Isidore.; Wolff, Ella.; Zimmerman, Charles S., -- 1896-1983.; Yivo Institute for Jewish Research -- Archives.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union -- Archives.
5767221
- Pauline Newman, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  #2 R.I. 1. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on January 19 and 26 and February 2, 1965. 66 pages. [Folder 1 of 2]
- Pauline Newman, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  #2 R.I. 1. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on January 19 and 26 and February 2, 1965. [Folder 2 of 2]
- Abraham Goldman, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  #2 R.I. 2. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on January 24, 1964. Typed Yiddish. 6 pages.
- Louis Lipsky, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  #2 R.I. 3. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on October 20, 1963. Typed Yiddish. 23 pages.
- Hyman Rogoff, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  #2 R.I. 4. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on November 17, 1963. Typed Yiddish. 17 pages.
- Benjamin Rabinovitch, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  #2 R.I. 5. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on December 23, 1963. Typed Yiddish. 46 pages. [Folder 1 of 2]
- Benjamin Rabinovitch, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  #2 R.I. 5. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on December 23, 1963. Typed Yiddish. [Folder 2 of 2]
- Joseph Gutterman, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  #2 R.I. 6. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on December 13, 1963. Typed Yiddish. 12 pages.
- Julius Gershin, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  #2 R.I. 7. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on December 26 and 27, 1964. Typed Yiddish. [Folder 1 of 2]
- Julius Gershin, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  #2 R.I. 7. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on December 26 and 27, 1964. Typed Yiddish. [Folder 2 of 2]
- Ella Wolff, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  #2 R.I. 8. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on December 27, 1963. 19 pages.
- Abe Belson, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  #2 R.I. 9. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on December 7, 1963. Typed Yiddish. 39 pages.
- Charles Zimmerman, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  #2 R.I. 10. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on November 13 and 20, and December 11, 1964. 72 pages. [Folder 1 of 2]
- Charles Zimmerman, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  #2 R.I. 10. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on November 13 and 20, and December 11, 1964. [Folder 2 of 2]
- Louis Nelson, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  #2 R.I. 11. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on October 5, 1965. Typed Yiddish. 21 pages.
- Adolph Held, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  #2 R.I. 12. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on February 15 and 22, May 9 and 23, and June 6, 1964. Typed Yiddish and English. 113 pages. [Folder 1 of 2]
- Adolph Held, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  #2 R.I. 12. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on February 15 and 22, May 9 and 23, and June 6, 1964. Typed Yiddish and English. [Folder 2 of 2]
- Isidore Wisotsky, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  #2 R.I. 13. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on October 26, 1963. Typed Yiddish. 113 pages. [Folder 1 of 3]
- Isidore Wisotsky, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  #2 R.I. 13. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on October 26, 1963. Typed Yiddish. [Folder 2 of 3]
- Isidore Wisotsky, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  #2 R.I. 13. Interviewed at YIVO Institute on October 26, 1963. Typed Yiddish. [Folder 3 of 3]